## Verdict

**Use B’s idea, but not a token-count high-water mark.**

The robust unit is the **Moonshine line**, keyed by `lineId`. Moonshine keeps the same `lineId` during revisions, allows only one active line per stream, and sends `LineCompleted` when the speaker pauses; after completion, that line’s text is no longer revised. ([GitHub][1])

### Why A breaks

A assumes token position remains stable:

```text
stablePrefix has K words
emit snapshot[K..]
```

That is *not safe* when earlier words merge or split:

```text
gon na             // K = 2
gonna home         // still 2 tokens
```

A emits nothing and permanently loses `home`.

```text
gonna              // K = 1
going to work      // 3 tokens
```

A emits `to work`, although `to` belongs to the revision of `gonna`.

Punctuation, contractions, hyphens, numbers, and languages without simple spaces can cause the same drift.

## Recommended state machine

Keep state **per `lineId`**:

```kotlin
data class StreamingLineState(
    val lineId: Long,
    var previousRawTokens: List<Token> = emptyList(),
    var emittedCount: Int = 0,
    var revisionCrossedFrontier: Boolean = false
)
```

On each `LineTextChanged`:

1. Tokenise the **raw Moonshine text**.
2. Find the token longest-common-prefix between the previous and current snapshot.
3. Only emit tokens that:

   * existed in the previous snapshot,
   * remain unchanged in the current snapshot,
   * occur after `emittedCount`.
4. Keep the newest one or two words pending as an unstable tail.

Conceptually:

```kotlin
val common = commonPrefixLength(previousRawTokens, currentRawTokens)

if (common < emittedCount) {
    // Moonshine revised something already emitted.
    revisionCrossedFrontier = true
} else if (!revisionCrossedFrontier) {
    val safeEnd = maxOf(emittedCount, common - HOLD_BACK_TOKENS)
    commit(currentRawTokens.subList(emittedCount, safeEnd))
    emittedCount = safeEnd
}

previousRawTokens = currentRawTokens
```

On `LineCompleted`:

* If no revision crossed the emitted frontier, commit the remaining tokens and reset.
* If it did cross, *do not recover by token count*. Either drop the remaining uncertain tail or use a unique anchor recovery described below.

This gives roughly a **one-snapshot delay**, but prevents the full-transcript replay.

## Why high-water token count is *not* enough

A count high-water mark only tells you how many tokens existed, not which tokens they were.

It fails when:

* two tokens merge into one;
* one token splits into two;
* the same number of tokens is completely rewritten;
* punctuation becomes a separate token;
* an interim snapshot briefly shrinks;
* Moonshine revises and appends in the same callback.

Use token count only **after validating that the prefix tokens still match**.

## Optional anchor recovery

When a revision crosses the emitted frontier, store the last three or four raw emitted tokens as an anchor.

Search for that exact sequence in the revised snapshot:

* **One unique match:** resume after it.
* *No match or several matches:* emit nothing more from that line and reset at `LineCompleted`.

Repeated phrases such as “the patient said the patient…” can make anchors ambiguous, so this must fail closed.

## Important extra failure modes

**Sanitiser feedback loop:** Diff raw Moonshine text first. Apply capitalisation, punctuation and spacing only to the outgoing delta. Never compare sanitised output against the next raw snapshot.

**Typing composition:** Do *not* call `finishComposingText()` for every voice delta. That would repeatedly finalise the word the user is typing. Queue voice output while an active composing word exists, then flush after the word is committed.

**Write ordering:** Key presses and voice commits must use one serial editor-mutation queue, ideally the Input Method Editor main thread. Otherwise two valid commits can arrive in the wrong order.

**Caret movement:** Decide what happens when the user taps earlier text. Blindly using the current selection can put later speech into the middle of the paragraph.

---

## UX choices to decide

### 1. Commit cadence

**Stable-word:** Commit after a word survives two snapshots, with one-word holdback. Slight delay, but far fewer bad partial words and revisions.

*Immediate:* Lowest delay, but Moonshine revisions will cross the committed frontier much more often.

### 2. Pause behaviour

**Pause finalises the line:** `LineCompleted` flushes the remaining tail and creates fresh state for the next utterance. This matches Moonshine’s own segment boundary.

*Keep one transcript across pauses:* Better continuity, but greatly raises drift, replay and punctuation problems.

### 3. Microphone lifetime

**Continuous until mic tap:** Voice Activity Detection ends each utterance but keeps listening. Best match for typing and speaking side by side.

*Auto-stop after silence:* Saves power and avoids accidental listening, but users must restart dictation after thinking pauses.

### 4. Capitalisation and punctuation

**Editor-context formatting:** Format only the new delta based on the characters around the insertion point. User deletions and edits remain authoritative.

*Moonshine-only formatting:* Simpler and consistent with recognition output, but may produce bad caps after typed text or deleted sentences.

### 5. Voice–typed spacing

**Smart boundary:** Inspect the character before and after the cursor; add a space only when needed and attach punctuation without a leading space.

*Literal transcript spacing:* Easier implementation, but commonly produces joined words or double spaces when typing and speech alternate.

### 6. User typing an unfinished word

**Queue voice briefly:** Hold voice deltas while the keyboard has an active composing word, then insert after that word. Keeps autocorrect and gesture typing intact.

*Force-finish composition:* Voice appears faster, but can break the word the user is currently typing.

### 7. Cursor moved for editing

**Suspend voice insertion:** Buffer speech while the selection is away from the expected insertion point; resume or flush when the user returns or stops the mic.

*Follow current cursor:* Speech always appears immediately, but can suddenly land inside text the user is correcting.

### 8. Revision conflict

**Fail closed:** Once a revision crosses already-emitted tokens, stop streaming that line and resume after the next pause. May lose a few final words, but never pastes old text again.

*Anchor recovery:* Usually saves more speech, but repeated phrases can still make the recovery uncertain.

**My default bundle:** stable-word commits, one-word holdback, raw-before-sanitiser diffing, continuous mic, pause resets the line, queue during active composition, and fail closed on frontier drift.

I could not store this project update as memory because memory was disabled after using the GitHub connector in this chat.

[1]: https://github.com/moonshine-ai/moonshine?utm_source=chatgpt.com "GitHub - moonshine-ai/moonshine: Very low latency speech to text, intent recognition, and text to speech, for building voice agents and interfaces · GitHub"
